<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-25T23:22:02-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Firstflight HFOSS</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/hfoss/2018/01/24/firstflight-hfoss.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Firstflight HFOSS" /><published>2018-01-24T11:04:54-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-24T11:04:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/hfoss/2018/01/24/firstflight-hfoss</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/hfoss/2018/01/24/firstflight-hfoss.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;hello&quot;&gt;Hello!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wooo! Website exists, very exciting. This site is built on Jekyll using the Merlot theme and is hosted on GitHub Pages. For the sake of posterity some advice on setting up a jekyll site (talking to you future me who has forgotten things work!). Once you get it &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/&quot;&gt;installed on your OS&lt;/a&gt; and have your &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages repo setup&lt;/a&gt;, then you probably want to pick a theme. If you go to your settings for the pages repo you will find a nifty option for themes, that include previews. If you want to change the theme and see it locally then change the theme section in your _config.yaml file to the theme name your using. Then if you look in your Gemfile you will find helpful comments that explain you uncomment the gem “github-pages” line and comment out the jekyll gem. If you don’t comment out the jekyll gem it will yell at you, as I found out the hard way by not reading fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;firstflight&quot;&gt;Firstflight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the other things in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ritjoe/hfoss/wiki/firstflight&quot;&gt;Firstflight assignment&lt;/a&gt;; I use Matrix now to connect to the IRC channels I’m in including #rit, #rit-foss, and #ritlug. If you too want to get setup with Matrix I suggest using &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/article/17/5/introducing-riot-IRC&quot;&gt;Justin Flory’s tutorial&lt;/a&gt; as that’s how I got setup. My username there is gen1e. I’m already on the HFOSS mailing list and I have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/reginatl&quot;&gt;GitHub account&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve also &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ReginaTL/hfoss&quot;&gt;just forked the HFOSS repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Hello!</summary></entry></feed>